Finding Aid for the Ana Bégué de Packman papers, 1870-1960 LSC.1491
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ana Bégué de Packman papers
1870-1960
UCLA Library Special Collections
Packman, Ana Bégué de
LSC.1491
1 linear feet (1 oversize box)
Ana Bégué de Packman (1882-1973) served as Secretary of the Historical Society of Southern California from the 1930s through the 1950s. The collection consists of Packman's photographs, newspaper articles, manuscripts, genealogies, maps, ephemera, and correspondence pertaining to the history of the city of Los Angeles, California missions, and Southern California ranchos and adobes.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Online Items Available note for the link to the digitized materials.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary Louise, Bernice, and Col. James L. Packman, 1977.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942335363606533
Biography
Ana Bégué de Packman (1882-1973) was a fifth-generation descendant of Maria Luisa Dominguez and Juan Francisco Reyes, former alcalde of El Pueblo de Los Angeles. She was also a descendant of Maximo Alaniz, who arrived in Los Angeles in 1769 and became the first grantee of Rancho San Jose de Buenos Aires (now Westwood and the University of California, Los Angeles). She served as the Secretary of the Historical Society of Southern California from the 1930s through the 1950s, where she was actively engaged in educational outreach programs, speaking engagements, and assisting in restoration efforts for various California landmarks. In addition to her duties as secretary for the Historical Society, Packman was the curator of Casa Figueroa, a historic adobe built by Don Ramon Figueroa prior to the arrival of Anglo-Americans.
Packman was an avid collector of historic photographs, newspaper articles, and ephemera relating to the history of Southern California, especially missions, ranchos, cattle brands, adobes, and early Los Angeles landmarks. She was also the author of several publications, including Leather Dollars: Short Stories of Pueblo Los Angeles, a collection of reminiscences of early California passed down from her family and published in 1932; and Early California Hospitality: The Cookery Customs of Spanish California, With Authentic Recipes and Menus of the Period, published in 1938.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Ana Bégué de Packman's collection of photographs, newspaper articles, manuscripts, genealogies, maps, ephemera, and correspondence pertaining to the California missions, Southern California adobes and ranchos, and the city of Los Angeles. Many of the photographs are reproductions of images taken by anonymous photographers, though reproductions of the work of C.C. Pierce & Company and Edward Vischer may also be found in the collection.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence, 1929-1965 (.5 box)
Los Angeles, ca. 1850-1962 (2.5 boxes)
California missions, ca. 1880-1965 (2.5 boxes)
Ranchos and adobes, ca. 1845-1962 (3 boxes)
Miscellaneous, ca. 1850-1976 (3 boxes).
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Ana Bégué de Packman papers (21 items).
Ranches -- California -- Photographs.; Missions, Spanish -- California -- Photographs.; Women historians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Packman, Ana Bégué de -- Archives
- Correspondence, 1929-1965; .5 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence addressed to Packman, principally relating to her role as the secretary for the Historical Society of Southern California, curator of Casa Figueroa, and an independent historian.
  - Corespondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Corespondence, 1929-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Corespondence, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Corespondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Corespondence, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Corespondence, 1941-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Corespondence, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Corespondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Los Angeles, ca. 1850-1962; 2.5 boxes
  Photographs, clippings, notes and Packman's own manuscripts relating to the history of Los Angeles and Los Angeles County. Most of the photographs are reproductions, though some may be original. Arranged alphabetically by folder title. See box 14 for a folder of oversize newspapers clippings about Los Angeles, mostly historical in nature.
  - Adams Boulevard, ca. 1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Photographs of the Adams / Figueroa area. Images include Judge Silents' residence, and the Lucien Napoleon Brunswig mansion at 3528-30 West Adams Boulevard.
  - Aliso Street, ca. 1870-1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Photographs. Images include: oldest fan palm in Los Angeles, located on the Ramirez property; Mellus Row, former location of Los Angeles' first City Hall (ca. 1885-1923); Old Sonora Town; burros carrying wood to market that had been gathered by Sonorans from Rancho Los Feliz (ca. 1870); and photographs of artistic renderings of the area.
  - B'Nai B'rith Synagogue, ca. 1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Photographs of the synagogue on W. Ninth and Hope Streets.
  - Bradbury Building, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes, and a copy of the floor plan.
  - Broadway, ca. 1880-1900 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Clippings, notes, and photographs. Images include: Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU) building at 401 N. Broadway; view from Hill and Court Streets showing N. Broadway residences and Hotel Aberdeen (ca. 1895); view of S. Broadway taken from the Olive Street Hill (ca. 1880); Bradbury Building at 304 S. Broadway; and various street scenes, including prominent buildings and businesses.
  - Casa Figueroa, ca. 1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Casa Figueroa event cards, announcements and photographs. Photographs include: the adobe on Jefferson and S. Figueroa Streets; the 1934 dedication ceremony at Casa Figueroa; portraits of Ana Begue de Packman.
  - Cemeteries, ca. 1914-1920 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Photographs. Images include: Rancho Buena Vista cemetery under excavation; Pio Pico tomb (ca. 1920); Workman monument at Rancho La Puente (ca. 1914); Catholic Calvary cemetery on North Broadway; and the tomb of Robert Carlisle at the first Protestant cemetery.
  - Chinatown, ca. 1890-1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Clippings, notes, and photographs. Images include: early views of Chinatown residents and Chinese settlements; Los Angeles Street; Apablaza House; members of the ceremonial Chinese Dragon troupe resting before the La Fiesta Parade (ca. 1902); and Peter Johnson of Chinatown (ca. 1890s).
  - Churches (1 of 2), ca. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Assorted printed materials.
  - Churches (2 of 2), ca. 1870-1923 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Photographs. Images include: First Baptist Church (founded 1874); Christian Church of Christ; First Congregational Church (ca. 1875); Church of Nuestra Señora la Reina de Los Angeles (ca. 1886); Cathedral of St. Vibiana (ca. 1888); First Methodist Episcopalian Church (ca. 1905); First Presbyterian Church and Trinity Methodist Episcopalian (ca. 1880); First Methodist Episcopalian Church on Broadway (formerly Fort Street); Congregational Church and the home of Justice of the Peace, John Trafford; St. Athanasius Church (ca. 1874); B'Nai B'rith Synagogue; First Presbyterian Church and Jewish synagogue on the corner of Second Street and Broadway (ca. 1870s); and others.
  - City Hall and Civic Center, ca. 1905-1926 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Photographs. Images include: old City Hall on Broadway near Second Street (ca. 1905); City Hall and Civic Center (ca. 1926); Spring Street.
  - Clubs, ca. 1936-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Printed ephemera and photographs. Images include: Ebell Club building on S. Broadway near Seventh Street; Woman's Club House; and Sunset Club.
  - Commercial Street, ca. 1870 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Photographs.
  - Father John Philip Conneally, S.J., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Letter to Packman from Father Philip Conneally, S.J. Includes several group photographs of school-age children associated with Father Conneally.
  - County Courthouse, ca. 1860-1900 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Clippings, notes and photographs. Images include: Red Sandstone Courthouse on Temple and Buena Vista Streets; negatives and prints taken from Courthouse Hill (ca. 1867), including views of the Clock Tower Courthouse, Main Street, the Masonic Temple, and neighboring buildings.
  - Downey Road, ca. 1920 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Photograph of a residence on Downey Road; advertisement for Farmers and Merchants National Bank of Los Angeles.
  - Eighth Street, ca. 1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Photograph of pedestrians crossing Eighth Street and S. Broadway; photograph of the Abbotsford Inn on Eighth Street, which later became the first Methodist Episcopalian Church.
  - El Pueblo, ca. 1936 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Clippings, notes and Packman's research materials.
  - Fifth Street, ca. 1887-1905 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Photographs. Images include: Los Angeles Examiner building on Fifth Street and Broadway; irrigation ditch in Central Park (Pershing Square); Hazard's Pavilion on W. Fifth Street, opposite Central Park.
  - Figueroa Street, ca. 1905, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Printed ephemera and photographs. Images include: first woolen mill in Los Angeles; pigeon farm (ca. 1905) on Pasadena Avenue and North Figueroa; the Stimson / Maier House on S. Figueroa (earlier known as Pearl Street); and Figueroa street scenes. Includes a Warner's film studio promotional card for the movie Life with Father (the back features a photograph and biographical sketch of Mary E. Foy, first woman librarian of the Los Angeles Public Library).
  - First Street, ca. 1870-1900 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Notes and photographs.
  - Fort Moore Hill (1 of 2), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Manuscripts, notes, and a typewritten letter from Major General E. S. Adams of the War Department addressed to Bert H. Cocks, in response to Cocks' letter requesting information about Fort Moore.
  - Fort Moore Hill (2 of 2), ca. 1880-1900 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Photographs. Images are principally of homes on Fort Moore Hill (present-day Fort Moore Place), Bunker Hill, and Court Street (no longer in existance).
  - Fourth Street, ca. 1903 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Photographs. Images include: Reverend Edward Hildreth's home on the corner of Fourth and Hope Streets; Chamber of Commerce Building on Fourth and 404 S. Broadway (ca. 1903).
  - Grand Avenue (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Photographs of the B. F. Coutler home at 215 N. Grand Avenue, L. J. Rose home at Fourth Street and Grand Avenue, and Hotel Melrose at 140 S. Grand.
  - Hill Street, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Photograph of the 800 block of Hill Street.
  - Hollywood Bowl campaign event for Republican presidential candidate Alf M. Landon, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hospitals, ca. 1880-1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Notes, correspondence, and printed materials related to the Sisters of Charity. Photographs include: Sisters' Hospital on Beaudry Hill; Sisters of Charity St. Vincent's Hospital on Beaudry near Sunset (ca. 1888); county hospital located at 1416 Naud Street between Ann and Sotello Streets; Don Cristobal Aguilar's adobe on North Spring Street (ca. 1895) in Sonora Town, Los Angeles, where the first charitable hospital was established by the Sisters of Charity; and the Good Samaritan Hospital on Seventh and Figueroa Streets (ca. 1905).
  - Hotels, ca. 1870-1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Notes, clippings and photographs. Images include: St. Charles Hotel and the New Queen Restaurant located at 314 and 316 N. Main Street; Bella Union Hotel on Main Street (ca. 1873); Hotel Lankershim on Broadway and Seventh Street (ca. 1904); Main Street, the former site of the St. Charles Hotel (ca. 1937); Biltmore Hotel on Fifth and Olive Streets; hotel on Spring and Fourth Streets; Westminster Hotel; Hollenbeck Hotel; and Nadeau House.
  - Main Street, ca. 1870-1938 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Clippings, notes and photographs. Images include: various street scenes; Fiesta Parade; St. Charles Hotel (ca. 1875); El Dorado Store in the Lan Franco building; Forty-Niners' Procession on the 4th of July in front of the U.S. Hotel (ca. 1875); Abel Stearns residence on Baker Block on N. Main Street; Russian Electric Baths (ca. 1880); Temple, Spring, and Main Street junction (ca. 1887); Farmers & Merchants National Bank building on Main and Commercial Streets; volunteer fire department display in commemoration of the centennial celebration of American Independence (ca. 1876) on N. Main Street near Commercial; Haas family at the John B. Haas ranch on Main between Washington and Adams Boulevards; and others.
  - Mayors, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Newspaper or magazine photographs of portraits of the mayors of Los Angeles, including: W. H. Workman, John Bryson, H. T. Hazard, Fred Eaton, T. E. Rowan, Frank Rader, Owen McAleer, A. C. Harper, W. D. Stephens, George Alexander, H. H. Rose, C. E. Sebastian, F. T. Woodman, and M. P. Snyder.
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Miscellaneous photographs and ephemera. Includes photographs of the view from Mt. Lowe, aerial photographs of the city and downtown businesses, and unidentified homes.
  - National Soldiers' Home, ca. 1905-1933 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Photographs and two articles, including one on William Edward Sawtelle. Images include: The Old Soldiers' Home during a 1905 Memorial Day review; a speaking engagement with President McKinley; and a photograph labeld "Sonoma" dated 1915.
  - Olive Street, ca. 1880 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Photographs of Olive Street Hill near Third Street, and steet views south from Fifth Street.
  - Parades, ca. 1870-1920 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Clippings and photographs. Images include: cars and carriages decorated with flowers for the La Fiesta and Fourth of July parades (ca. 1873-1919); President McKinley and his wife at the Los Angeles La Fiesta parade of 1901; and various groups from parade processions, including Franciscan priests, Citrus Belt groups, trade unions, Ladies of the Chamber of Commerce, fire departments, caballeros, and military veterans (ca. 1873-1919).
  - Parks, ca. 1880-1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Clippings, notes and photographs. Images include: Hollenbeck Park; Charles Prudhomme pointing to the Bartolo Pass; Photograph of a stream in Central Park / Pershing Square (ca. 1880); calla lily field; Shutes Park on Main and Washington Street; Westlake Park and Hotel del Monte; Exposition Park; City Gardens on San Pedro Street and Eighth (ca. 1896); Elysian Park hillside near Griffith Park (ca. 1895); East Lake Park watering hole; Armistice Day procession (ca. 1931); and banana plants, date palms, twin palms, and pepper tree berries.
  - Pico Boulevard, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Photographs of the Charles Forman home at 1015 West Pico Boulevard.
  - Plaza District, ca. 1880-1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Printed ephemera, photographs, notes and manuscripts. Images include: Plaza Church and the main plaza; Pico House; Los Angeles City Water Co. and Gas Works buildings; negative of Don Manuel Galón, Aztec soap maker, on Olvera Street; Tallyho stagecoach on the Sierra Madre-Pasadena-Los Angeles route, and passengers in front of the Pico House (ca. 1884); retailers adjacent to Teatro Merced; the Pedro Ybarra homestead on N. Broadway and W. College Streets (ca. 1895); and Commander Stockton's headquarters.
  - Post Office and Federal Building, ca. 1890-1910 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Photographs. Images include: old post office on Main Street near Fifth (ca. 1895); Downey Block (ca. 1905) before its demolition for construction of a new post office, completed in 1910; Los Angeles Post Office and Federal Building on Main and Temple Streets (ca. 1910).
  - Residences, ca. 1880-1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Photographs. Images include: Doheny residence; E. T. Earl residence; Marco Hellman residence; Morris brothers residence; Charles Forman residence and ranch at Toluca Lake; and others.
  - Santa Monica, ca. 1890-1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Watkins' New Series photographs of Santa Monica, and photographs of Long Wharf and the shoreline.
  - Schools (1 of 2), ca. 1923-1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Assorted printed materials and notes.
  - Schools (2 of 2), ca. 1850-1900 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Photographs, including group portraits of 19th century pupils and instructors. Images include: school on Temple near High Street and Fort (Broadway); Second Street School (ca. 1895); the first Los Angeles high school (ca. 1898); Rosedale School (ca. 1895); Los Angeles County Teacher's Institute (ca. 1884), including Hattie Gower, Mary L. Gower, Henry C. Gower, Olive Wilson, Ira Moore, J. W. Hiuton, and S. A. Waldron; the Florence School (ca. 1885); Lordsburg College in La Verne (ca. 1900); Sisters of Charity Pioneer Girls School (ca. 1856); Padres Parochial School; St. Vibiana's School (ca. 1893); and St. Vincent College, taken by Edward Vischer (ca. 1869).
  - Second Street, ca. 1880 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Photographs. Images include: Second and Hill Streets; Second Street tunnel on the west end of Figueroa Street; and local businesses.
  - Seventh Street, ca. 1880-1900 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Photographs and notes. Images include the State Militia Parade on Seventh and Hope Streets (ca. 1889).
  - Sixth Street, ca. 1880-1930 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Photographs of streets and buildings.
  - Spring Street, ca. 1880-1941 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Clippings and photographs.
  - Temple Street, ca. 1850-1900 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Photographs. Images include: Horticultural Pavilion (ca. 1878); Juan Temple adobe; Temple Street west from Broadway, with views of residences and the Gillette Pavilion; junction of Spring, Main, and the original Temple Street (ca. 1863); Juan Temple adobe (ca. 1869); Poundcake Hill (later Telegraph Hill) and Justicia Street (ca. 1870) north from Temple Street, including the residence of Jack Brundidge (aka the Bilderrain Home); and others.
  - Theaters, ca. 1890-1910 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Photographs of the Childs' Grand Opera House and Belasco Theater.
  - Third Street, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Photographs. Images include: Angel's Flight trolley on Third and Hill Streets (before 1930) showing the Hill Crest Inn; and local businesses.
  - Washington Boulevard, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Newspaper clipping showing two contrasting photographs of Washington Boulevard.
  - Water, ca. 1932 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Notes and photographs. Images include: Charles Jenkins, Mr. Spiegel, Don de la Guerra, Judge Pleasance, and Mr. Dodson; old water mill on S. Alameda Street; old mill on Bale Ranch; an Indian zanjero ("keeper of the water ditch"); site of Los Angeles Water Company's office; city water tank in the old Plaza; and the city water wheel constructed on the property of Rafael Carrabajal and Marta Reyes.
  - Wilshire Boulevard, ca. 1905-1926 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Newspaper clipping featuring photographs of Wilshire Boulevard and Western Avenue in 1906 and 1926; images of homes and businesses along Wilshire.
- California missions, ca. 1880-1965; 2.5 boxes
  Photographs, clippings, notes and Packman's own manuscripts relating to the history of Southern California missions. Arranged alphabetically by folder title. See box 14 for a folder of oversize newspapers clippings about the missions, including a 1934 publication entitled Catholic Missions, published by the Society for the Propagation of the Faith.
  - Mission Asistencia de San Antonio de Pala (Sub-mission of Mission San Luís Rey), ca. 1929 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Newspaper clippings from 1929. Postcards and photographs of Mission Asistencia de San Antonio de Pala, a submission of Mission San Luís Rey, including interior and exterior shots. Photograph of an 1883 etching by Henry Chapman Ford.
  - Mission Asistencia de San Bernardino (Sub-Mission of Mission San Gabriel), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Pamphlet and three photographs.
  - Mission Asistencia de Santa Ysabel (Sub-Mission of Mission San Diego de Alcalá) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Photograph of a man on horseback in front of the main church.
  - Mission La Exaltación de La Santa Cruz, ca. 1904 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Postcard and sepia photographs of a sketch of Mission La Exaltacion de La Santa Cruz (ca. 1904), and a photograph of a painting by Toussaint.
  - Mission La Purísima Concepción de María Santísima, ca. 1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Booklets and brochures with information on the restoration of the mission, notes, and photographs of the structure and grounds.
  - Mission Nuestra Señora Dolorosisima de la Soledad, ca. 1959 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Souvenir program from the First Annual Soledad Mission Fiesta on October 11, 1959; photographs.
  - Mission Nuestra Señora Reina de Los Angeles (Old Plaza Church)--Miscellaneous, ca. 1906-1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Clippings and notes. Personal letter to Packman from Tom Owen of the United States Navy.
  - Mission Nuestra Señora Reina de Los Angeles (Old Plaza Church)--Photographs, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Assorted photographs of the mission and the priests. Includes interior and exterior shots with views of the plaza.
  - Mission San Antonio de Padua, ca. 1934-1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Booklets, brochures and fliers. Photographs of the buildings, grounds and ruins.
  - Mission San Buenaventura, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Printed materials and photographs of the buildings and grounds.
  - Mission San Carlos Borromeo de Carmelo--Miscellaneous, ca. 1914 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Brochures, postcards and clippings.
  - Mission San Carlos Borromeo de Carmelo--Photographs, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Photographs of the buildings, grounds, and ruins, including interior views.
  - Mission San Diego de Alcalá--Miscellaneous, ca. 1930 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Clippings and printed ephemera.
  - Mission San Diego de Alcalá--Photographs (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Photographs of the buildings, grounds and ruins.
  - Mission San Fernando Rey de España, ca. 1909-1936 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Business card of T. R. Griffith and other printed ephemera, including invitations to events, brochures, announcements and postcards. Typed account of an inventory describing the condition of the Church; assorted typed histories and speeches; and photographs.
  - Mission San Francisco de Asís (Mission Dolores) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Photographs of Mission Dolores showing the cemetery, neighboring ruins, front entrance of the mission, and the Argüello monument.
  - Mission San Francisco de Solano (Sonoma Mission), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Photographs of exterior before and after restoration.
  - Mission San Gabriel Arcángel--Miscellaneous, ca. 1909-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Assorted printed ephemera, notes and clippings.
  - Mission San Gabriel Arcángel --Photographs (1 of 2), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Photographs of adobes, streets, and structures in the area surrounding the mission; photographs of the mission buildings and grounds.
  - Mission San Gabriel Arcángel--Photographs (2 of 2), ca. 1870-1930 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Images include: Carrie Winters, Levy Maxson, Harry Sanderson, and Margaret Maxson; Eulalia Pérez (widow of a former Spanish-Mexican soldier), who lived and worked as a cook at Mission San Gabriel; adobes of Judge Clinton Gibbs and Volney E. Howard from 1872-1880 (later owned by the Purcell family, from 1880 onward); and assorted ruins.
  - Mission San José de Guadalupe, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Photographs of the administration building before and after restoration.
  - Mission San Juan Bautista, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Photographs and postcards.
  - Mission San Juan Capistrano, ca. 1933-1951 (Box 5, Folder 8)